Educational Psychology, The University of Texas at Austin

□+1 736 865 0618 | ■ sooyong109@gmail.com | • sooyongl/

Professional Summary

I am a psychometrician with expertise in applying modern statistical theories and techniques. My research interests are in the development and application of statistical models such as such as structural equation modeling (SEM), multilevel modeling (MLM), and item response theory (IRT). Recently, I have focused on Bayesian estimation to model the relationships among variables.

Education

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, Texas 2017-Present

PH.D.

· Major in Quantitative Methods

Korea University Seoul, Republic of Korea

2014-2017

• Major in Educational Statistics and Measurement

Research experience

CGS PhD Career Pathways project

Graduate Research Assistant

2018/9-2019/5

· Data analysis for surveys to collect data on the career pathways of past and present STEM and humanities PhD students.

President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

Graduate Research Assistant

PRESIDENT'S AWARD FOR GLOBAL LEARNING (PAGL)

2019/1-2019/8

• Designing a culturally appropriate mobile application to increase mental health literacy and self-care habits among South Korean young adults

COE Full-Time Tenured and Tenure-Track Faculty

Graduate Research Assistant

2019/9-2019/12

· Data analysis for surveys of graduate programs of education at the University of Texas at Austin

MAAT package development project

Graduate Research Assistant

NORTHWEST EVALUATION ASSOCIATION (NWEA)

2019/9-2020/5

• Development of MAAT package for Computerized Adaptive Testing for Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

FLPS projectGraduate Research Assistant

IES GRANT 2021/9-Present

• Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2020/6-2020/8

• Internship for developing Shiny app for Embeded Standard Setting

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2021/6-2020/8

· Internship for developing ESS package for Embeded Standard Setting

Teaching experience

EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling

Teaching Assistant

PROFESSOR TIFFANY WHITTAKER

2020/1-2020/

EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling

Teaching Assistant

PROFESSOR TIFFANY WHITTAKER

2021/1-2021/5

Publications

Cory L. Cobb, Charles R. Martínez, Jr., **Sooyong Lee**, Tae Kyoung Lee, & Elma I. Lorenzo-Blanco, (2021). Acculturation trajectories differ by youth age at arrival and time in residency among Latino immigrant families in a US emerging immigrant context. *International Journal of Intercultural Relations*, 81, 79-93.

2022

- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker, (2022). Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*, 29, 23-35.
- Seung Choi, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Christina M. Schneider, Jay Lee, & Garron J. (2022). maat: An R Package for Multiple Administrations Adaptive Testing. *Applied Psychological Measurement*, 46-1, 73-74.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2022). DIF Detection With Zero-Inflation Under the Factor Mixture Modeling Framework. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*, 82-4, 678-704.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Parallel Process Latent Growth Modeling with Multivariate Confounders/Suppressors. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Kahyun Lee, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Application of Associative Discrete-Time Survival Analysis Using Latent Transition Specification. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*.,

2023

- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Fully-Latent Principal Stratification. *The Annual Meeting of the Psychometric Society* (in print)
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2023). Bayesian MIMIC for DIF Detection under Violation of Equal Variance Assumption. *Educational and Psychological Measurement* (in review)
- Tiffany A. Whittaker, Laura Stapleton & **Sooyong Lee** (2023). A Tutorial for Obtaining Item Response Theory Results from Structural Equation Modeling in Mplus Software with Rating Scales. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal* (in review)
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Comparison between Bayesian or ML in FLPS with Small Sample Sizes. (in progress)
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Multidimensional FLPS. (in progress)

Presentation

Poster

- Kejin Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Youngri Lee (2018-5). An Alternative Approach to Discrete-Time Survival Analysis for Meaningful Interpretation. Modern Modeling Methods conference (MMM), Storrs, CT.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Sehee Hong (2018-7). Exploration of LCA conditions in Latent Class with Low Proportion. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), New York, NY.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2020-4). Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Suhwa Han (2020-7). Item selection and trait estimation methods in CAT with item leakage. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), College Park, MD.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2021-4). DIF Detection with Zero-Inflation under the Mixture Modeling Framework. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.

Conference presentation

Daniel Lewis & **Sooyong Lee** (2021-4). A Comparison of Two ESS Cut Score Estimation Algorithms. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), Baltimore, MD.

- Garron Gianopulos, Jay Lee, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, & Seung W. Choi (2022-4). The Impact of Item Pool Size and Item Pool Distribution on Student Ability Estimates for a Hybrid Interim-Summative CAT. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- Jay Lee, M. Christina Schneider, Garron Gia, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, Seung W. Choi (2022-4). The Impact of Item Pool Size and Item Pool Distribution on Student Ability Estimates for a Hybrid Interim-Summative CAT. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.

Sooyong Lee, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022-7). Fully-Latent Principal Stratication. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Bologna, Italy.

Program

GRshiny: Graded response model

Shiny application

2022

https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/GRShiny/

Embeded Standard Setting

Shiny application

2021

https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/ESS_test/

maat package

R package

ouchage

• https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/maat/index.html

FLPS package

R package

achage

clavaan package

R package

2023

Fellowship & Awards_

William Hays Endowed Fellowship

Fellowship

2020-21

Benjamin & Dorothy Fruchter Excellence Award

Award

2021-22